In the last lecture we created our axios instance,
Son konferansta X-ists rneimizi yarattk.
now it's time to be able to send the requests there.
imdi, oradaki talepleri gnderebilmenin zaman geldi.
Now let's figure out where we do this.
imdi nerede yapacamz bulalm.
Well in our burger builder container, there we have this method where we handle the purchase continuation.
Bergere Boulder konteynerimizde kovalamaca devam etmeyi ele alacamz bu yntem var.
Right now we're showing this you continue alert,
u anda biz size alerji yapmaya devam ettiinizi gsteriyoruz.
now of course we don't want to show you continue in the final application,
Elbette, son bavurunuzda devam etmek istediinizi gstermek istemiyoruz.
we probably want to navigate the user to some checkout form.
Muhtemelen, kullancy onun iin kontrol etmeye ynlendirmek istiyoruz.
We haven't learned how to load different pages in our single page app
Tek sayfamza farkl sayfalar nasl ykleneceini rendik.
and yes, pages in our single page app sounds strange you'll see how that works soon,
Tek sayfa uygulamalarmzdaki evet sayfalar garip geliyor, bunun nasl ie yaradn greceksiniz.
and we also haven't learned how to handle a form input, how to validate this and so on.
Ayrca bir form girdisini bunun nasl dorulanaca ve bunun gibi nasl ele alnacan rendik.
So for now there won't be a checkout form,
imdilik bir kontrol formu olacak.
we can simply take the order as it is and store it like this with some dummy data appended to it in
Siparii olduu gibi alp veritabannda ona eklenmi baz kukla verilere sahip
the database.
olarak saklarz.
So to do that, let's comment out this alert line here and instead of this place here, I want to send my data
Bunu yapmak iin, burada bu uyar izgisini hazrlayalm ve burada grntler yerine verilerimi srtma gndermek
to my backend, I want to make this HTTP request. So in the burger builder file, we should import our own
istiyorum ve bu HTP isteini herhangi bir Bergere faturasna sunmak iin kendi X-ists
axios instance
rneini almalyz.
so I'm going to import axios from and now I need to go all the way up to the root folder and there from
Bundan sonra, x yl sonra kk klasrne kadar gitmem gerekiyor ve orada
the axios-orders.js file, this is going to use our configured axios instance.
X yllk siparilerden js dosyas yaplandrlm x 'rneini kullanacak.
Now we can use that in the purchaseContinueHandler to send the request to our own backend.
imdi bunu kat kovalamaca ileyicisine kendi paketimize gndermek iin kullanabiliriz.
Now for storing data, we should use a post request and therefore we use the post method on that instance.
Artk veri saklama iin bir yayn istei kullanmal ve bu nedenle bu rnekte post yntemini kullanyoruz.
Now the URL is of course now our base URL plus whatever we're adding here,
imdi, elbette ki sizin taban artk tabanmza, art ne olursa olsun burada ekliyorsunuz.
and that's the cool thing about firebase I said that it uses as MongoDB like structure,
Firebase gzleri, Mongo D-B'nin yaps gibi kulland gzel ey.
we don't actually have tables here
Aslnda burada tablolarmz yok.
we just have json like nested structure and if you send a request to something like this URL
sevmesini salyoruz ve byle bir ey iin bir istek gnderirseniz emirlerimizi keseriz.
slash orders,
Jason'n yuvalanm yapy
it's going to create our orders node and store our orders beneath that node
Emirler dmmz yaratacak ve siparilerimizi bu dmn altnda saklarz.
and this is exactly what I want to do.
Ve tam da bunu yapmak istiyorum.
I'll add slash orders here and now for firebase only, there is a special thing, you need to add .json
Buraya ve imdi ate bariyeri iin eik izgi siparileri ekleyeceim, yalnzca nokta Jason eklemeniz gereken zel bir
here.
ey var.
This is the end point you just need to target for firebase to function correctly.
Bu, atee dayanklln doru ekilde almas iin hedeflemeniz gereken son nokta.
Of course in your next project you probably have your own backend or you use some other service and
Tabii ki bir sonraki projenizde muhtemelen kendi arka uunuz var ya da ortalama bir hizmet
you need to choose the appropriate endpoint there.
kullanyorsunuz ve orada uygun son noktay semeniz gerekiyor.
For firebase it's any node name of your choice .json.
Firebase iin setiiniz datt'n herhangi bir dm ad var.
So that's the URL I want to send a request to, the URL which gets appended to my base URL
Jason Yani sizsiniz ya da dirsek veya ssmn tabanna eklenen yolun tabanna eklenen d l
or the path which gets appended to our base URL,
ye bir istek gndermek istiyorum.
now we also need to send some data and that data of course should be our order for the given burger configuration.
imdi de baz veriler gndermemiz gerekiyor ve bu veriler elbette belirli bir Bruegel yaplandrmas iin bizim sipariimiz olmaldr.
Now the burger configuration is stored in the state
imdi burger konfigrasyonu devlette saklanr.
here, we have the ingredients, we have the total price
Burada toplam fiyata sahip olduumuz malzemeler var.
so we get everything we need here,
Yani burada ihtiyacmz olan her eyi alyoruz.
so that's super simple.
Bu ok basit.
We can create a new order object, a javascript object which has ingredients
erii olan bir javascript nesnesi olan yeni bir sipari nesnesi oluturabiliriz.
and here I simply want to use this.state.ingredients and which should have a price,
Ve burada sadece bu devlet katk maddelerini kullanmak istiyorum ve bir fiyata sahip olmalym.
this.state.price, total price excuse me and just a little side note of course for your production ready
Bu devlet fiyat toplam fiyat ve kesinlikle retim iin veya uygulama iin tabii ki
application, you should definitely calculate that final price on the server because you probably
kk bir yan not sunucuda nihai fiyat hesaplamanz gerekir nk
have your product stored on the server there to make sure that the user isn't manipulating the code
muhtemelen rn sunucu orada kullanc isn ' t gndermeden nce
before sending it and manipulates the price which you're using.
kodu maniple etme ve kullandnz fiyat deitirme.
Still here I'm going to use that price, again
Hala burada, fiyat tekrar kullanacam.
be aware that this of course is not a set up you would use on a real app,
Elbette bunun gerek bir uygulamada kullanacanz bir kurulum olmadna dikkat edin.
there you would recalculate the price on the server.
Orada sunucudaki fiyat yeniden hesaplarsnz.
Now let's say for our order we also need some additional information which we can't fetch right now because
imdi bir sipari iin onun iin bir kontrolmz yok nk yine de baz kukla
we don't have a checkout form but which I still want to fill on the backend with some dummy data.
verilerle arka planda doldurmak istediimiz u an getirilebileceimiz baz ek bilgilere ihtiyacmz var diyelim.
So there we have some customer data maybe, so customer, could be a javascript object where we have something
Yani baz mteri verilerimiz var, bu nedenle mteri bir isim gibi bir ey bulduumuz bir
like a name,
javascript nesnesi olabilir.
So here, this is Max Schwarzmuller, that's my name,
Bu senin yaptn Max Schwartz MILLER Bu benim ismim.
choose your name, of course.
Elbette sizin adnz sein.
Then we might have an address where we have something like street, the test street,
O zaman sokan clz caddesi gibi bir adrese sahip olduumuz bir adres olabilir.
you might guess that I'm not living there and like a zipcode rolling over the keyboard and maybe countries
Orada yaamak istemediimi, klavyeden yalpalama kodunu ve belki de benim iin olan lkeleri Almanya gibi hissettiimi
for me, that's Germany and feel free to add any additional data here.
tahmin edebilir ve buradan ek bilgi ekleyebilirsiniz.
We also might have that e-mail address so let's test@test.com here
O e-posta adresimize sahip olabiliriz, bu yzden test edilmi dot com'u buradan test edelim.
and let's maybe add a number field next to customer delivery method which should be fastest so that
Ve muhtemelen hzl teslimat ile en ucuz arasnda bir seim ya da buna benzer bir eye
we have like a choice between fastest possible delivery and cheapest or something like that.
sahip olmamz iin, mteri datm ynteminin yannda bir numara alan ekleyelim.
So just some dummy order data,
Bu yzden sadece baz kukla sipari verileri.
feel free to pick any data you want.
stediiniz verileri semekten ekinmeyin.
We're later going to add a checkout page where we can actually fill those with some live by using a
bir form kullanarak bunlar canl bir ekilde doldurabildiimiz bir deme sayfas ekleyeceiz.
form
Ardndan,
but for now let's simply build our dummy order like this. This now is the order I want to store on the
Fakat u anki kukla sipariimi u an arka uta saklamak istediim sipari gibi ina etmeye
backend
balayalm.
so for the order here, I'm going to pass this as a second argument for the post request.
Bu yzden emir yl iin post talebin ikinci bir argman olarak geeceim.
So this is the data which gets sent to this path
Yani bu, Poth'a gnderilen veriler.
and now let's add then method to see our response
Ve imdi yantn grmek iin Methot ekleyelim.
and I'm just going to log the response here for now.
Ve yant burada imdilik kilitleyeceim.
And let's also add a catch method where I also want to log the error for now,
Ve hepsi, hatay imdilik kaydettirmek istediim yakalama yntemidir.
we're going to update both methods in a second.
Her iki yntemi de bir saniye iinde gncelleyeceiz.
So let's see if this now works,
imdi bunun ie yarayp yaramayacana bakalm.
we got our post request in place,
Yerinde posta talebimiz var.
we're sending a dummy order,
Sahte bir emir gnderiyoruz.
we set up the axios instance and we created the firebase project.
Eriim rneini kurduk ve gvenlik duvar projesini hazrladk.
Let's head over to our burger application and let's build a burger here,
imdi Bruegel bavurumuza gidelim ve burada bir burger hazrlayalm.
maybe this one let's click order now
Belki bu imdi sipari tkla.
and now up on continue, the requests should be sent.
Ve imdi yukar ve devam isteklerini gnderilmelidir.
So let's click continue and that's looking good,
yleyse devam edelim ve bu iyi grnyor.
I'm getting back a response with status 200
Yant durumunu 100'e geri alyorum.
so let's check out firebase.
yleyse gvenlik duvarn kontrol edelim.
It should update this page automatically and you should see the orders node in which you now see this
Bu sayfay otomatik olarak gncelletirmeli ve buradaki ifreli ad
cryptic name here.
grdnz sipari dmn grmelisiniz.
Now to use the post method, firebase is automatically creating and managing a list here
Artk posta yntemi firebase otomatik olarak bir liste oluturup ynetmek iin buray kullanyor.
and each list item simply get a unique ID assigned and created by firebase automatically.
Ve her listede yalnzca otomatik olarak ate baras tarafndan atanan ve oluturulan benzersiz bir kimlik bilgisi yoktu.
If we expand this object we see the order data
Bu nesneyi geniletirsek, sipari verilerini grrz.
we actually passed with the address, the customer data, the delivery method and the ingredients of the burger
Aslnda mteri verileri teslimat yntemine getik ve hamburger ve malzemelerin ierikleri
and the ingredients looked good to me,
bana iyi bakt.
meat, salad, bacon that looks a lot like the burger we actually built here.
Gerekten burada ina etmi olduumuz burgere benzeyen, et salatas pastrmas.
So that's pretty great.
Bu ok iyi.
We got our burgers saved on the back,
Srtmzdaki burgerleri kurtardk.
we got our orders saved here
Siparilerimizi burada sakladk.
but the cool thing is of course that this data is staying here.
Elbette, serin bir ey u ki bu veriler burada kalyor.
If we reload the app, we reload this html file and therefore of course lose the application state because
dosyasn yeniden ykleriz ve bu nedenle javascript durumu ortadan kalktndan tabii ki uygulama durumunu kaybedersiniz.
the javascript state is gone
Yep'i yeniden yklersek bu HDMI
but of course our state on the server is still there.
Ancak elbette sunucumuzdaki devlet hala orada.
So now we could fetch the orders and output them to the user
imdi siparileri alp kullancya verebiliriz.
and in a real application, we would also as a producer or as the business owner,
Gerek bir uygulamada, bir retici olarak iletme sahibinin dinlenmesi gibi.
we would also probably handle the orders now and send that burger to the customer.
Muhtemelen emirleri imdi halledeceiz ve o burgeri mteriye yollayacaz.
So that's a POST request
Yani bu bir POST istei.
before we go onto error handling and that stuff, let's make sure that we also present something to the
Hata ileme ve bor konularna balamadan nce, istek yoluna devam ederken de
user whilst the request is on its way
kullancya bir ey sunduumuzdan emin olalm.
and then let's make sure that we also get some data from the backend.
Ardndan, arka utan baz veriler de alacamzdan emin olalm.